Now that we had such a close look at stateful and stateless components,
Biz devletin tam ve devlet daha az bileenleri yakndan baktmzdan vgyle sz etti.
we should have a look at the component lifecycle, something I mentioned but we haven't taken a closer
Bahsettiim bir eyin bileen mrne bir gz atmalyz ancak daha yakndan
look.
incelemedik.
So what is the component lifecycle?
Peki bileen yaam dngs nedir.
In the end when react creates a component for us, that means instantiates and renderers that for us,
Sonunda Yates'e tepki gsterdiinde, bizim iin bir bileen, yani bizim iin birden
it runs through multiple lifecycle phases and we can define methods in a stateful component, only in
fazla yaam dngs aamasndan getii ve yntemleri ve ilev bileenlerini tanmlayamayacanz iin yalnzca devletin tam bileenleri iindeki
stateful components because you can't define methods and functional components we can define methods
bir devletin tam bileeninde yntemleri tanmlayabildiimiz rnekler ve oluturucular anlamna gelir. baz yaam dngs
which react will execute which allows us to run some code during some of these lifecycle phases.
aamalar srasnda baz kod altrmamza izin veren execute ilevine tepki gsteren yntemler bulabilirsiniz.
Let's have a look at all these component lifecycle methods and let's see when which of these is executed.
Bu bileen yaam dngs yntemlerine bir gz atalm ve bunlarn hangisinin yrtldn grelim.
Important as I just mentioned, these are only available to stateful components not in stateless components
Az nce bahsettiim gibi nemli olan ey, yalnzca devlet tarafndan daha az bileenler kullanlmayan ancak devletin tam bileenleri.
and there, we got the following methods.
Ve u yntemleri bulduk.
Now these are a lot as you can see, constructor componentWillMount,
imdi yapc bileeni greceiniz kadar ok ey var.
WillUpdate, DidMount, render.
Gncelletirme, montaj ileyiini yapacak m?
You might know some of these, some of these might be kind of intuitive about when they get executed but
Bunlardan bazlarnn idam edildiinde olduka sezgisel olabileceini biliyor olabilirsiniz,
let's still analyze when which of these methods is executed
ancak bu yntemlerden hangisinin yrtldnde hala Analise'dir.
and let's have a look at the component creation first.
Ve nce bileen oluturma blmne gz atalm.
Not all these lifecycle hooks are executed there, not all these methods are executed during creation,
Tm bu yaam dngs kancalar yrtlemezler, bu yntemlerin hepsi oluturulma srasnda idam edilmez.
only these methods are executed,
Yalnzca bu yntemler uygulanr.
Constructor, WillMount, DidMount and render.
Oluturucu montaj takar ve iler.
Now let's take a closer look at that creation component lifecycle process,
imdi, oluturma bileeni yaam dngs srecine daha yakndan bir gz atalm.
first of all the constructor gets executed and the constructor actually is a default ES6 class
Her eyden nce yapc altrlr ve yapc aslnda her alt snfn varsaylan bir
feature,
varsaylandr.
it's not a method defined by react, what react does though is it creates the component in the end,
Sonunda bir bileen oluturmasna ramen, yeniden davranmann ne yaptn yeniden aktarmayla tanmlanan bir yntem deildir.
So it instantiates it and it parses on any props this component receives to the constructor.
Bylece onu rneklendirir ve bu bileen kurucunun ald herhangi bir sorundan geer.
Therefore if we implement this constructor method and we don't have to, thus far in our demo project
Dolaysyla, bu kurucu yntemi uygularsak ve imdiye kadar demo projemize gerek
we didn't,
kalmadk.
if we do implement the constructor method we do have to call super and pass on props, this calls the
Yapc yntemini uygularsak, sper'i armal ve pervaneyi geirmeliyiz bu arlar
constructor of the parents class,
st snfn yapcsna.
and since we can only implement this method in stateful components, the parent class is this component
Ve bu yntemi yalnzca durum bilgisi olan bileenlerde uygulayabildiimiz iin st snf, tepki verdikten
object we imported from react. And by calling super and passing on props, things like this.props which
sonra ithal ettiimiz bu bileen nesnesidir ve sper ararak ve pervane eyleri gibi bu sahte paralara
we then need to use anywhere else in the component get populated or managed by react.
geerek, baka bir yerde kullanmak zorunda olduumuz eyleri doldurur veya ynetiriz. tepki.
So always call super and pass on props if you implement the constructor. What else may you do here and
zaman sper arn ve proplarn zerine gein; burada baka ne yapabilir ve tabii ki istee baldr.
that of course is optional,
Yapcy uygularsanz her
you may initialize the state in the constructor,
Yapcdaki durumu ilk duruma getirebilirsiniz.
we did this by simply defining a state property
Bunu sadece bir devlet mlkiyeti tanmlayarak yapmtk.
but you could also define this property here in the constructor and in older code snippets which had
Ancak burada bu mlknz yapcda ve kullandmz yeni javascript zelliklerine eriebilen
access to the new javascript features we were using,
daha eski kod snippet'lerinde de tanmlayabilirsiniz.
You saw that your comment
Yorumu grdn.
did initialize state in the constructor.
Oluturucuda durumunu balatmtm.
What you should never ever do there is cause side effects.
Orada hi yapmamal niye yan etkiler oluyor.
What are side effects? For example reaching out to a web server,
rnein bir web sunucusuna ulamann yan etkileri nelerdir.
so requests which come back and then edit the state of your application, that is the side effect.
Bu nedenle geri gelip sonra uygulama verilerinizin durumunu dzenleme istekleri Yan etkiyi grn.
You should not do that in the constructor because this may lead to a re-rendering of your application
Yapcda yapmamalsnz, nk bu, uygulamanzn gerek bir ekilde oluturulmasna ve dolaysyla iki
and hence to performance issues,
performans sorununa neden olabilir.
it may also lead to your state becoming unpredictable. After constructor, another function gets
Ayrca durumunuzun ngrlemeyen hale gelmesine neden olabilir. Oluturucuya, bir dizi fonksiyon
executed, this function is the componentWillMount method.
yklendiinde, bu ilev bileen monte edilecei anlamna gelir.
Now this is a method defined by react and it is available because we extend that component from the
ile tanmlanan bir metot ve bir yoldur nk bu bileen yeniden
react library. componentWillMount exists for historic reasons mainly, you don't really use it that
aktr ktphane bileeninden uzatacaz, nk tarihsel sebeplerden tr varolacak takviye esas olarak Artk sk sk kullanmyorsunuz.
often anymore.
imdi bu tepki
If you use it, you want to use it to update your state here,
Bunu kullanrsanz, durumunuzu gncellemek iin kullanmazsnz.
do some last minute optimizations but still you shouldn't cause side effects here,
Baz Lassman optimizasyonlar yapyorsunuz, ancak yine de burada yan etkilere neden olmamalsnz.
you shouldn't reach out to the web.
Web'e ulamamalyz.
Now as I mentioned, you don't really use it that often anymore,
imdi bahsettiim gibi, artk sk sk kullanmyorsun.
it still exists but chances are you won't implement it in your application. After componentWillMount,
Hl var, ancak uygulama teklif bileeninizde bunu uygulayamayacanz ihtimali var.
the component will render.
Bileen ileyecektir.
Now executing the render method does not mean that it accesses the real dom,
imdi render yntemini altrmak, gerek Dom'a erien l anlamna gelmiyor.
I will come back to how exactly react renders the real dom and updates to dom in this module again.
Tam olarak re-act'n gerek Dom'u nasl oluturduuna ve bu modlde Don iin gncellemelerin tekrar nasl yaplacana tekrar bakacam.
For now, you should know that render, executing the render method gives react the idea of what it should
imdilik, render yntemini yrten render'n, neye benzeyeceini gstermek iin neyin yarataca konusunda
render, how it would look like
fikir rettiini bilmelisiniz.
if it then reaches out to the real dom and manipulates it,
Eer o zaman gerek Dom'a uzanp maniple ederse.
depends on what does real dom looks like already.
Gerek Dom'un zaten nasl grndne bal.
If no changes need to be made, it doesn't go ahead and re-rendered it anyways.
Herhangi bir deiiklik yaplmas gerekmiyorsa, nne geilmez ve zaten nceden oluturulmutur.
But the render method is an important step because it clearly defines how your application or how this
Ancak render yntemi nemli bir admdr; nk uygulamanzn veya bu bileenin bir H'den nasl
component should look like from a html perspective.
grnd aka tanmlanmaktadr. T. erkek perspektifi.
So it's in the render method where you prepare and structure your jsx code, defining which content gets
Bu nedenle, bu bileen iin hangi ieriin oluturulduu tanmlayan GSX kodunuzu hazrlamak ve
rendered for this component.
yaplandrmak iin render ynteminde bulunur.
Now thereafter, react of course also knows which child components this component has, because in
Artk, elbette ki bu bileenin hangi alt bileenlerinde olduu gibi tekrar hareket ettiklerini
the end once you call render and define your jsx code it also knows which components you included in
gryorlar nk sonunda render ve GSX kodunuzu bulmak iin, oradaki bileenleri demo
there, like the persons component in our demo project.
projemizdeki kiinin bileeni gibi biliyor .
So it will then go ahead and render all these child components,
Dolaysyla devam edip tm bu ocuk bileenlerini oluturacaz.
basically executing this process for every child component and thereafter it will call componentDidMount
Temelde bu ilemi her bir alt bileen iin gerekletirir ve bundan sonra
to basically tell you that this component was successfully mounted.
bileen arr, temelde bu bileen baaryla monte edildiini syler.
Now there in componentDidMount,
imdi para takld.
you can cause side effects,
Yan etkilere neden olabilirsiniz.
this is the point of time where you want to reach out to the web for example to fetch some data.
rnein, baz verileri almak iin Web'e ulamak istediiniz zaman budur.
What you shouldn't do here is update the state though because that will trigger a re-render so that is
Burada yapmamalyz devlet gncellemek nk nceden ilenmi bir aklda tutulmas gereken bir
something you have to keep in mind,
ey veri tetikleyecektir nk.
don't call this.setState in componentDidMount,
Bu set durumunu balayan bileen olarak adlandrmayn.
this will trigger a re-rendering and if you're wondering how exact it would look like reaching out
gerek bir ileme neden olur ve Web'e uzanmak ve bu web eriimindeki
to the web and using the result from that web access, this is something we'll also have a look in this
zm kullanarak ne kadar net grneceini merak ediyorsanz, bu derste de bir gz atn.
course
Bu,
once we start adding web access to our applications. Now, it's nice to see this diagram here but it's
Uygulamalarmza web eriimi ekledikten sonra, burada bu emay grmek gzel ama yine
still very abstract,
de ok soyut.
so let's head back to our project and let's implement these hooks and maybe log something to the console
imdi projemize geri dnelim ve bu kancalar uygulamaya balayalm ve belki de
so that we can really see the flow of our application.
uygulamanzn akn grebilmemiz iin konsola bir eyler kilitleyelim.